<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short discourse (recommended to all our English divines) concerning the death of the witnesses in general, and the two witnesses in particular; : plainly shewing ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3584C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184159</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077623</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077623</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151715</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93210)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151715)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2273:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short discourse (recommended to all our English divines) concerning the death of the witnesses in general, and the two witnesses in particular; : plainly shewing ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Lambeth Place Library, London, England.</note>
                  <note>First, the chief and true reason of their death. -- Secondly, the manner how they are to be slain. -- Thirdly, the place where. -- Fourthly, the time when. -- Fifthly, by whom they are to be slain. -- Sixthly, the true reason why they are overcome, and why in particular by a war. -- Seventhly, who they are, and that they have already been slain. -- The conclusion.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestantism --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151715:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SHORT DISCOURSE (Recommended to all Our <hi>Engliſh</hi>
DIVINES) Concerning the Death of the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> in general, AND The
Two <hi>Witneſſes</hi> in particular; Plainly Shewing, 
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, <hi>The</hi> Chief <hi>and</hi> True <hi>Reaſon
of their Death.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, <hi>The Manner</hi> How <hi>they are to be
Slain.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Thirdly, <hi>The Place</hi> Where.</item>
                  <item>Fourthly, <hi>The Time</hi> When.</item>
                  <item>Fifthly, <hi>By</hi> Whom <hi>they are to be
Slain.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sixthly, <hi>The</hi> True <hi>Reaſon</hi> Why <hi>they
are</hi> Overcome, <hi>and</hi> why <hi>in particular by a</hi> War.</item>
                  <item>Seventhly, Who <hi>they are, and that they</hi> have
already <hi>been Slain.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</head>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>FIRST,</hi> The chief Reaſon of their Death is
not their Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry's <hi>Malice,</hi> as hath been generally ſuppoſed;
no, <hi>This</hi> is only the Secondary and Inſtrumental Cauſe thereof; the
<hi>True</hi> and <hi>Chief</hi> Reaſon of their Death, is, the
<hi>Neceſſity</hi> thereof; for, having <hi>Finiſhed</hi> their
Teſtimony, they <hi>Ought</hi> to die: New Evidence is <pb n="2" facs="tcp:151715:2"/>to
be given, therefore <hi>They</hi> are to be thruſt out of Court. <hi>Come
<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p Hither,</hi> ſaith the Text; this <hi>Great Voice</hi> was not made or
directed to them, (for <hi>They</hi> and <hi>Their</hi> Teſtimony were
ſlain:) But to the <hi>New-Riſen</hi> Witneſſes, inveſting
<hi>Them</hi> with Power, and authorizing <hi>Them</hi> to give in
<hi>Their</hi> Evidence, and to commence a <hi>New</hi> Diſpenſation. Was
the Death of <hi>Christ</hi> (for I muſt all along make a Compariſon
therewith) <hi>Neceſſary</hi> to put a Period to the Jewiſh
Diſpenſation and Ceremonies, then <hi>Their</hi> Death was neceſſary to
put an End to the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> I mean the Firſt Chriſtian
Diſpenſation? No Diſpenſation can be <hi>finiſhed</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
Death, and without a <hi>Death</hi> there can be no <hi>Reſurrection,</hi>
and without the intire Diſſolution of the <hi>Old,</hi> there can be no
<hi>New</hi> Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. So 'tis ſelf-evident, That the Death of the
Witneſſes is <hi>Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary;</hi> for would the Old Diſpenſation
have ſerved God's Purpoſes, and the World's Neceſſities, 'tis certain,
they had not been ſlain. 'Twas impoſſible it ſhould be otherwiſe.
<hi>Father,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>if poſſible, let this Cup paſs
from me.</hi> But ſince it did not paſs, what doth his Death im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, but
that 'twas <hi>impoſſible</hi> it ſhould be otherwiſe? And ſince the
Head could not (according to God's Appointment) eſcape Death on account of
Finiſhing the Old, and Commencing a New Diſpenſation; 'tis much more
impoſſible for the Body or Members to avoid Drinking of the ſame Cup,
when they are in the ſame Circumſtances and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>Secondly,</hi> As to the Manner <hi>How</hi> they
are ſlain. To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; That Sickneſs, Perſecution, or any other
Abuſe or Alteration in the <hi>ſame</hi> Subject, Body, or Conſtitution,
is not <hi>This ſpecial Death</hi> they are to undergo. My Reaſons are,
<hi>First,</hi> If <hi>This ſort</hi> of Death might have ſerved the Turn,
<hi>Then</hi> Chriſt had had no Occaſion to have prayed, <hi>Father, if
poſſible,</hi> &amp;c. For it had been <hi>poſſible</hi> and feaſible
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to have Effected the Great Deſign, without his Drinking the Bitter
Cup: For, a Scourging, a Whipping, or any other Abuſe to his Sacred Perſon,
would have ſerved the Turn. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Would <hi>This ſort</hi> of
Death have ſerved the Deſign of God, <hi>then</hi> they might have died and
roſe <hi>often,</hi> becauſe they might be perſecuted and abuſed
<hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</hi> But 'tis ſelf-evident, That <hi>This Death</hi> ought to be
Circumſtanced ſo, and be of ſuch a Nature, that they may die but
<hi>once,</hi> becauſe Chriſt died but <hi>once,</hi> and, indeed, no Man
can die twice. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Would <hi>This ſort</hi> of Death have done
the Buſineſs, <hi>then</hi> they would have riſen <hi>Bare grain,</hi>
with their Old Bodies; and this contradicts the true Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of a
Reſurrection. There ought to be nothing Old in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, but
<hi>all Things New.</hi> And Chriſt himſelf in relation to this 
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151715:2"/>Great Scene, ſaith, <hi>Behold, I make all Things New.</hi>
Sickneſs or Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is not Death, Reſtitution is not Reſurrection.
The Powers and Conſtitution of the Old Church and State ought <hi>not</hi> to
be impaired or weakned, but <hi>totally diſſolved,</hi> to make it Death,
and <hi>not</hi> reſtored or repaired, but <hi>abſolutely Rebuilt,</hi> to
make a Reſurrection, otherwiſe the true Analogy of Death and Reſurrection
will not be anſwer'd: And when I ſay the Church and State are thus
abſolutely to be <hi>diſſolved,</hi> I think, I need not ſay, that both
Head and Member ought ſo to be, for I comprehend both under the Denomination
of Witneſſes.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As to the Place <hi>where.</hi> It
ought not to be in an Inland Country: And therefore not in <hi>Rome, Piedmont,
Germany, Bohemia, Hungaria, France,</hi> &amp;c. as <hi>ſome</hi> have
thought. I freely own, that ſome Members or Parts of the Body of the True
Church, and in a common Senſe, the Witneſſes of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> in all
theſe Countries have been abuſed, perſecuted and ſlain; but
<hi>Theſe</hi> were not final, but intermediate Deaths; and as the Church can
have no <hi>Abortive</hi> Birth, ſo no <hi>immature</hi> Death. But,
<hi>Secondly,</hi> As ſuch Abuſes and Perſecutions have no Title to the
Denomination of <hi>This Special</hi> Death; ſo the Places are very improper
for it: Becauſe, it muſt be acknowledged, that Inland Countries are unfit
to begin a Diſpenſation in; and nothing is more certain than that the
Witneſſes are ſlain on purpoſe, that a New Diſpenſation may
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence. Further, The Head was ſlain in the <hi>East,</hi> the Body ought
therefore to be ſlain in the <hi>West:</hi> But this will be more confirmed,
if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider; The Holy Writings make mention of Two Harveſts, the
Firſt in the <hi>East,</hi> and by conſequence, the Latter in the
<hi>West;</hi> for the uſual Cuſtom of Reapers confirms it, who uſually
begin at the End of a Field; The World is this Field. The Firſt Harveſt was
the Jewiſh Ceremony, and Pagan Idolatry, they were to be Reaped down; ſo
the Reapers of thoſe Times, <hi>viz.</hi> the Old Witneſſes began
<hi>Their</hi> Work in the Eaſt, and <hi>Now</hi> the Chriſtian
Superſtition and Papal Idolatry is to be reaped down; ſo 'tis convenient
the Reapers, that is, the New-riſen Witneſſes begin their Harveſt in
the <hi>West.</hi> Nature will direct us in this Affair. The Sun and the
Goſpel are Fellow-Travellers: They Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh their Journey in the
<hi>West,</hi> and then ſet out again for the <hi>East.</hi> But
<hi>Laſtly,</hi> The Witneſſes, and their Two chief Repreſentatives are
to be ſlain in their <hi>own chief Country,</hi> and <hi>own chief City:</hi>
Becauſe Chriſt was ſlain in <hi>Judea</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
otherwiſe there will not be a due Conformity betwixt the Body and the Head.
And as for the Place being called <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Aegypt,</hi> it
imports Little, becauſe 'tls <hi>Spiritually</hi> called ſo; for
<hi>Judea,</hi> by the Prophets, has often been <hi>Spiritually</hi> called
<hi>Sodom,</hi> and <pb n="4" facs="tcp:151715:3"/>ſo very well may the Witneſſes
Country with a <hi>Salvo</hi> to their Holy Function.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> As to the Time <hi>When.</hi> To
this I anſwer, 'Tis <hi>When</hi> they have come to their Journey's End,
<hi>When</hi> they have <hi>Finiſhed</hi> their Courſe and Teſtimony:
<hi>When</hi> they have Acted that Part, and Publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thoſe Truths Heaven
has appointed them to Publiſh; <hi>When</hi> the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> or
<hi>Guardian State</hi> of 1260 Years are Ended; <hi>When</hi> the Church is
come to her adult State, <hi>When</hi> ſhe is grown a Woman, or come <hi>Ad
Menſuram Staturae Chriſti adulti:</hi> This is called the Fulneſs of
Time: And <hi>Then</hi> it is they are ſlain, <hi>Then</hi> it is that a
Solemn Period is put to the Old Diſpenſation. <hi>Then</hi> it is a Great
Voice is heard out of the Temple of Heaven from the <hi>Throne,</hi> ſaying,
<hi>GEGONE,</hi> it is done, or <hi>Finiſhed;</hi> But what? <hi>Their</hi>
Teſtimony, or the Old Diſpenſation. There are <hi>Two Great Voices</hi>
in Scripture, particularly to be taken Notice of; The <hi>First</hi> is,
<hi>Conſummatum est,</hi> made by Chriſt <hi>Viva Voce</hi> on the Croſs:
The <hi>Other</hi> is this <hi>Gegone</hi> from the <hi>Throne, (Rex
patitur.)</hi> As the <hi>First</hi> was utter'd at the Death of the Head, and
finiſhed the Jewiſh Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, ſo the <hi>Latter</hi> of courſe
muſt be made at the Death of the Body (or the Witneſſes) and
<hi>finiſh</hi> the Chriſtian Diſpenſation, I mean the Firſt
Diſpenſation: For we are to come from <hi>Strength</hi> to
<hi>Strength</hi> until we come to God in <hi>Sion.</hi> As to the Calculation
of Numbers and Figures, 'tis a Barren Study, and may miſguide us, but
Reaſon and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance never can. Yet in relation to this, the Year of the
Witneſſes Death being fixed (as hereafter) will eaſily fix all the
Reſt.</p>
               <p n="5">V. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> By <hi>Whom</hi> they are Slain. They
are not ſlain by a Foreign Enemy or Nation, they are not ſlain, (I ſpeak
of this laſt Special and Particular Death) by the Pagan or Papal Power, as
ſome have unadvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly affirmed: For, though theſe may rejoice at their
Death, and in other Caſes be Criminal enough; yet to give them their due,
they have no hand in <hi>this Last</hi> Tragedy. It needs no Proof that the
Pagan and Papal Powers are repreſented by the Beaſts that riſe out of the
Sea and Earth; but 'tis plain, that neither of theſe Beaſts are concerned;
For the Text is expreſs to the Contrary, <hi>That the Beast which riſes out
of the Bottomleſs Pit,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> Wickedneſs in general, or Satan)
<hi>ſhall make WAR with Them, OVERCOME Them, and SLAY Them.</hi> Now ſince
theſe Three Beaſts have Three diſtinct Characters, ſure none will
confound them, and make them all one and the ſame. Not to mince any further
the Matter, the Truth is, We, their <hi>Friends</hi> and Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, have
ſlain them. The Reaſon is, Chriſt was ſlain by his Own 
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151715:3"/>Countrymen and Friends. He had his Wounds from the Hands of
his Friends, and from thoſe of his Own Houſe. Thus with Zeal, whilſt the
<hi>Jews</hi> wait for, and Expect their <hi>SAVIO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R,</hi> and the
Chriſtians their <hi>Two Witneſſes;</hi> The <hi>First,</hi> when
<hi>He</hi> came ſlew the <hi>First,</hi> and the <hi>Latter,</hi> when
<hi>They</hi> came ſlew the <hi>Latter.</hi> The <hi>Homines ex Tribubus,
&amp; Populis &amp; Linguis &amp; Gentibus,</hi> are their Friends, <hi>Coguati
in Religione.</hi> Men of the ſame Reformed Religion, and of the ſame
Nation. But the <hi>Jucolae Terrae</hi> are their Enemies and Foreigners, who
rejoice at their Death, being of a Differing Perſuaſion, and whom theſe
Witneſſes tormented. In ſhort, the Firſt are Proteſtants, the Latter
Papiſts, and had not their Friends ſlain them, there had been no due
Conformity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Circumſtances of the Death of the Head, and the
Body.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. <hi>Sixthly,</hi> The <hi>True</hi> Reaſons
<hi>Why</hi> they are <hi>Overcome,</hi> and <hi>Why</hi> in Particular by a
<hi>War,</hi> are as follows: But, <hi>Firſt</hi> I muſt acquaint the World
of a particular Thing they have taken little Notice of, which yet gives
extraordinary Light to this great Myſtery, and that is this, That <hi>This
War</hi> is, and muſt of Neceſſity be an <hi>Inteſtine War:</hi> For,
How can it be otherwiſe? Since their Friends and Countrymen, Men of the
ſame Religion and Nation muſt ſlay them. This has been ſufficiently
proved above, and cannot be denied. I hope therefore they will not ſay, that
is a Foreign War made in the ſame Nation, by Citizen and Countrymen amongſt
themſelves, and it can be no other; for the <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culae Terrae,</hi> who are
Foreigners, are only Spectators, not Actors in the Affair. But there is another
<hi>Great</hi> Reaſon, little inferior to this, which fully clenches the
Matter, and makes it impoſſible it ſhould be other than a Civil War, and
that is this, <hi>The Witneſſes</hi> (in Conformity to the Head) <hi>are to
riſe again after they are ſlain.</hi> Now, had it been a Foreign Enemy, or
Men of another Religion that had ſlain them, they had <hi>never riſen
again,</hi> but Church and State had both fallen into the bottomleſs Pit, and
been utterly deſtroyed. Theſe Things are very plain. But to return to the
Reaſons, <hi>Why,</hi> &amp;c. conſidering War therefore neither as Civil
or Foreign, but indefinitely, and abſtractedly; I ſay not only a a
<hi>War,</hi> but <hi>Victory</hi> thereby, are Circumſtances little leſs
neceſſary than their Death it ſelf: For ſince the Old Conſtitution
both of Church and State were wholly to be diſſolved, nothing leſs than a
<hi>War</hi> could do <hi>This,</hi> and done it ought to be, otherwiſe the
Old Diſpenſation could have no true and proper Period; ſome Alteration or
a Weakening of it would not anſwer, nothing but Death could ſerve the Turn,
that is, a Total Diſſolution. A Seizure by Conſpiracy would not ſerve,
nor could <pb n="6" facs="tcp:151715:4"/>a few Tumultuous Hands pull down the Building,
nothing but a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſault on all ſides could effectually do it; and
this did it indeed, and levell'd all with the Ground. But to come cloſer; The
Conſtable and Watch with Clubs and Staves may ſeize and overpower a
ſingle Perſon unarmed: But to pluck a King and High Prieſt from their
Throne, who are inveſted with Power and Force, nothing leſs than a
<hi>Greater</hi> Force could do this, that is, a <hi>War.</hi> And as to a full
Victory or Conqueſt it was no leſs neceſſary in reſpect of a due
Proceſs and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment. Stabbing or Aſſaſſination might indeed
procure Death, but then <hi>This ſort</hi> of Death would have wanted the due
and neceſſary Solemnity; but Chriſt was not Stabbed or
Aſſaſſinated (I ſpeak now in Relation to the Two Witneſſes) but
publickly Arraigned and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; and the Copy ought to agree with the
Original: So a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Victory over them was neceſſary, that the due
Solemnity of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs and Arraignment might take Place. In ſhort, the
Progreſſion of the Climax is exceeding Regular, the <hi>War</hi> and
<hi>Victory</hi> being <hi>highly</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to procure <hi>that</hi>
Death, the <hi>most</hi> neceſſary of them all.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. <hi>Seventhly, Who</hi> they are. They are the True
Church of Chriſt under the Denomination of Witneſſes; and when I ſay
the Old Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, the New Witneſſes, or the Witneſſes, I refer to
the Bulk or Body of the Building, and when I ſay the <hi>Two
Witneſſes,</hi> I refer to the Two chief Corner Stones; the whole Body is
of a Witneſſing Nature, and every ſingle Stone is a Witneſs: But the
Two chief corner Stones, by way of Excellency, are called, the <hi>Two
Witneſſes.</hi> Theſe repreſent the whole Body as a King and an High
Prieſt, the whole Nation; and as <hi>They</hi> repreſent the Power of the
Whole, ſo at the appointed Time <hi>They</hi> are choſe out to
<hi>finiſh</hi> the Power of the Whole. The Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a Building is
made by the Holy Spirit. And after 'tis ſaid, The Gentiles ſhall tread
under Foot the Holy City; 'Tis preſently added (as <hi>Beza</hi> renders it;)
<hi>Dabo Illam;</hi> (that is, <hi>Sanctam <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbem) Duobus Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Teſtibus
meis;</hi> that is, I will give the Care or Charge of my True Church to thoſe
my <hi>Two Witneſſes,</hi> and, as if it had been asked who theſe Two
Witneſſes were, the Anſwer is, <hi>Hi ſunt Duae Illae Oleae,</hi>
mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> and <hi>Joſhua.</hi> Now none can make any Thing
of theſe Two but a King and a High Prieſt. And though <hi>the Temple was
mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, and THOSE</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> the People) <hi>who worſhipped
therein:</hi> Yet I find the Text points no more but <hi>once</hi> to the
Multitude, and indeed 'twas needleſs, becauſe they had no Power: They are
under Care and Protection, but cannot repreſent <hi>that</hi> they
<hi>have</hi> not. And <hi>thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> 
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:151715:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>therefore are much miſtaken, who ſuppoſe a few common Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duals
ſlain in any Country, may anſwer the Death of the <hi>Two
Witneſſes.</hi> They make no Diſtinction betwixt the Body and Head: 'Tis
certain, the common Maſs, as <hi>living</hi> they have no Power, ſo their
<hi>Death</hi> can repreſent the <hi>finiſhing</hi> of none; I mean their
Death ſingly and apart; yet in Conjunction with their Head the TWO, I own
their Death adds to the Efficacy and Solemnity, and that they ought to fall at
the General Harveſt by the Angel's Sickle: Yet to compleat ſuch a ſolemn
Period, and to make it Full and Authentick, nothing leſs than the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn
Death of a <hi>King</hi> and an <hi>High Prieſt</hi> will do the
Buſineſs. For <hi>theſe</hi> being the Heads or chief Proprietors of
<hi>Power,</hi> are the moſt fit and proper Perſons to undergo the
Paſſive Solemnity of its Abrogation. NOW, <hi>ſuch</hi> a Thing has
happened amongſt <hi>us, viz.</hi> a King and an High Prieſt have been
ſlain, after an unparalell'd and uncommon Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or rather after a moſt
proper Manner, they were ſlain in the Face of the Sun with the higheſt
Solemnity, that all the World might take notice, that the Grand Period of the
Old Diſpenſation was <hi>finiſhed.</hi> And not only in this Point, but
in all other Circumſtances, as to <hi>Time,</hi> and <hi>Place,
Proceſs,</hi> and <hi>Arraignment,</hi> their Death exactly agrees with the
Text, and Counterpart. <hi>IN THE WESTERN PART OF THE WORLD, THESE-TWO
WITNESSES, REPRESENTATIVES OF THE TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH, OR WHOLE PROTEST ANT BODY,
IN THEIR OWN CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NTRY, BY THEIR OWN FRIENDS, AT THEIR OWN CHIEF CITY, WERE
OVERCOME, BY A WAR</hi> and <hi>SLAIN.</hi> God is True, and all the World are
Lyars. He hath told us, <hi>In the End it ſhall ſpeak and not Lye:</hi> Now
here the Viſion ſpeaks, and who can contradict it? This Truth deſerves to
be writ in Capitals of Gold, ſince it aſſerts the Veracity of God, which
fooliſh and vain Man has ſo long called in Queſtion. I own there are
ſeveral Perſuaſions, but no Matter by what Names we are called. There are
only Two Churches, a True and Falſe One, and I find the Holy Spirit takes
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of no more: Yet 'tis obſervable, the <hi>First</hi> is expreſt by
<hi>Four</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Denominations, <hi>viz. Tribus, Populi, Linguae, &amp;
Gentes;</hi> and the <hi>Latter</hi> but by <hi>One,</hi> viz. <hi>Jucolae
Terrae.</hi> Now poſſibly amongſt other Meanings, the Difference in
Opinion may be one that cauſeth this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction: But leaving this Enquiry
to the more Curious, let the <hi>Four</hi> be <hi>who,</hi> and <hi>what</hi>
they will, 'tis certain, <hi>theſe Two ſlain Witneſſes</hi> were the
Head of them all, and appointed by Heaven to <hi>finiſh</hi> their
<hi>Old</hi> State and Adminiſtration. The Church is in Two differing States,
<hi>First</hi> under the Minor or Guardian State, then under the <hi>Adult
State.</hi> And <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151715:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>theſe <hi>Two ſlain
Witneſſes</hi> finiſh the Minor, or Guardian State, being the <hi>Two
Last</hi> chief Proprietors of Power therein. And this gives great Light to
thoſe Congratulations of the Church on Chriſt's Arrival to his
<hi>Manhood</hi> in the Church, and by Conſequence on his Acceſſion to
the Throne. <hi>We Thank Thee, ſay they,</hi> Lord God <hi>Almighty, who art
and waſt, and art to come; Becauſe thou haſt taken to THY SELF</hi>
('twas in the Hands of Guardians before) Thy <hi>Great</hi> Power,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> This implies a <hi>leſſer</hi> Power in the former State.
The <hi>Millennium</hi> is nothing but the <hi>Manhood</hi> of Chriſt in his
Church, and when He comes to his <hi>Manhood,</hi> He is inveſted of courſe
with his <hi>Great Power.</hi> But I would not be miſtaken, I prefer the
Maſter before the Servants, and am far from making a Compariſon betwixt the
Death of the Two Witneſſes and that of Chriſt's, as to the Merit of it;
yet I muſt be forced to acknowledge (and the Holy Scripture will bear me out)
that <hi>Their</hi> Death is the true Counterpart of <hi>His,</hi> and ought to
be attended with much the like Circumſtances, <hi>viz.</hi> a Reſurrection
(not Literal) Aſcenſion, and New Diſpenſation. As to the Two Firſt,
the Text plainly mentions them, and the Laſt to me is as plain: For, when
<hi>John</hi> had eaten up the Book of the Old Diſpenſation, he was told,
That he muſt <hi>PROPHESIE AGAIN, before People, and Nations, and Tongues,
and many Kings.</hi> The Words <hi>Finiſhing</hi> Prophecy, and
<hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying again,</hi> illuſtrate one the other; nor can we think
they will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie <hi>again</hi> what they have <hi>finiſhed,</hi> but
turn over a <hi>New</hi> Leaf, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin a <hi>New</hi> Chapter. And now,</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding any former Opinion (which I ſhall not be
aſhamed to diſown) at preſent, the Truth ſhines ſo full in my Face,
that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherwiſe think, and do hope ſo will others, That the Death
of the afore-mentioned <hi>Perſons,</hi> was the <hi>True</hi> Death of the
<hi>Two Last Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> which were to die to <hi>finiſh</hi> the
Old Diſpenſation. Thoſe who have Objections, let them publiſh them. All
Chriſtians muſt own, That <hi>ſuch</hi> a Thing, if <hi>not</hi> done,
ſome Time or other, in ſome Place or other, <hi>must</hi> be done; and
ſince it <hi>must</hi> be done, let them produce better Reaſons if they
can, that <hi>This</hi> is not the Fact, or that it is <hi>yet</hi> to be done,
and I ſhall willingly acquieſce therein. But I am ſatisfied, they cannot.
It therefore being taken for granted, that the <hi>Two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes are
ſlain,</hi> and Old Diſpenſation <hi>finiſhed;</hi> the next
neceſſary Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence will be, that we are on the <hi>Premiſes</hi> of the
<hi>Millennium,</hi> and that the Downfall of <hi>Rome</hi> is juſt at the
Door. For <hi>This</hi> black Tragedy, as it withdraws the <hi>Old</hi> Scenes,
ſo it preſents the World with <hi>New</hi> ones, and opens a wide Door for
Light and Truth. But to conclude, I <pb n="9" facs="tcp:151715:5"/>ſhall endeavour to
bring the Thing yet cloſer, and make it yet a little more plain, by Summing
up the Whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</head>
               <p>There are a True and a Falſe Church, or Two Syncronizing
Powers enter the Stage of the World, theſe Two Powers are repreſented by an
inward and outward Court, the Latter perſecutes the Former all the Time they
are on the Stage; the Former are called Witneſſes, having this Name from
the Nature of their Office, which is of a Twofold Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; for they have a
Charge to give in, <hi>Teſtationem, &amp; Proteſtationem,</hi> to
Publiſh, and give their Evidence to Divine Truths, and Matters of Fact, and
to make Proteſtation againſt all Iniquity and Idolatry, and eſpecially
againſt the Perſecution of their Adverſaries. The Date of their
Adverſaries Power and theirs is equal, but during the greateſt part of
their appointed Time, being perſecuted and trodden under Foot, little
Strength or Power (though virtually in them) appears, but near the Expiration
thereof it exerts it ſelf, not only in order to pull down and oppoſe their
Adverſaries, but in order to be abrogated it ſelf. That which is <hi>under
Foot,</hi> and ſtands not <hi>up,</hi> cannot be thrown <hi>down;</hi>
therefore at laſt it <hi>ſtands up</hi> in order to be thrown down, but
withal, in order to <hi>riſe again,</hi> and not to be thrown in the Fire
like their Enemies. The Cedar and the Vine are lopp'd, that the Branches may
yield more Fruit, and flouriſh more abundantly. But to return, Theſe Two
Syncronizing Powers as at once they make their Entrance, ſo at once they make
their <hi>Exit,</hi> yet their reſpective Scenes are not preſently removed,
there is the ſame Diſtance of Time in Proportion, as betwixt the
<hi>Harveſt</hi> and the <hi>Vintage.</hi> The Harveſt (as uſual) begins
firſt, and the inner Court is pull'd down, that is, the Angel puts in his
Sickle (according to Command) and reaps the True Church, raiſes a War, cuts
down her Two chief Repreſentatives, burns her chief City, and inflicts many
other heavy Calamities upon her. Thus ends the <hi>Harveſt,</hi> and nothing
elſe is ſaid, only <hi>Demeſſa eſt Terra,</hi> The Earth was reaped.
Afterwards (in courſe) the <hi>Vintage</hi> comes, and the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Court is
pull'd down, and when the Angel had cut down the Grapes, the Text ſaith,
<hi>Miſit in Magnum Illum Lacum Excandeſcentiae Dei, He put them into that
great Wine-Preſs of the Wrath of God.</hi> The Truth is, after God hath
accounted with the <hi>True</hi> Church, he reckons with the <hi>Falſe</hi>
One, <hi>viz.</hi> with the Whore and her Worſhippers, and <pb n="10" facs="tcp:151715:6"/>both <hi>ſhe</hi> and <hi>her</hi> City are burnt with Fire. But
betwixt the City of the <hi>True</hi> Church, and that of the <hi>Falſe</hi>
One, there is this Difference, the Firſt is only burnt with the Fire of
<hi>Purgation,</hi> the Latter by the Fire of <hi>Indignation.</hi> And as to
the <hi>Firſt,</hi> that Text is fulfilled, which ſaith, <hi>Although I
fall, yet I ſhall riſe;</hi> for <hi>ſhe</hi> hath riſen again, and
ſhines very gloriouſly: But when the Latter falls (and her Grapes are
juſt ripe) <hi>ſhe</hi> ſhall never riſe again; But the Wrath of God
abideth on her for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi> So be it. And now I have demonſtrated
the Thing ſo plainly, I am very well ſatisfied, that though ſome
<hi>may,</hi> yet others will not believe: So <hi>That</hi> will be fulfilled
which was ſaid of Old; <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I work a Work in your Days, which ye
ſhall in no wiſe believe, although a Man declare it unto you,</hi> that is,
demonſtrate it. But I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude without a ſmall Reflection or two
more, both on our Enemies, and our ſelves, <hi>viz.</hi> When our City Flamed
about our Ears, and other publick Calamities befel us, our Enemies, the
<hi>Jucolae Terrae,</hi> rejoiced much to ſee us in ſuch deplorable
Circumſtances, under the Evil of our own Predictions; ſeeing us ſo low,
they thought we ſhould never riſe again to torment them with Truth;
therefore they ſent Gifts and were glad: And we inſtead of looking up to
Heaven, and being humble, charged our Enemies with our Miſeries, and
proceeded ſo far as to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord</hi> the ſame not in Braſs, but in
Letters of Stone, which indeed ought to be eraſed; for it was GOD that burnt
our City, and not <hi>They;</hi> but like true Men in Miſery, we were angry
with every Body, yes, with GOD to, and ready to flie in his Face, and charge
him with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, and a Forgetfulneſs of his Promiſes. Thus we laid
the Guilt every-where, but where it ſhould be, on our ſelves. Ignorant
Wretches! We neither underſtood the Methods of God or Nature. 'Tis God's
uſual Method to puniſh his own Child firſt, Judgment always begins with
the Houſe of God. And as to Nature, we would have had Corn, and not Reaped,
we would have had new Corn, and not Sowed; nay, we would have had Branches the
firſt Day the Tree was lopp'd, and new Corn the firſt Day the Seed was
ſown: So ignorant, and impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient we were. Well! our Harveſt has been got
in, we have ſuffer'd nothing but our Lot, and much leſs than we deſerved.
Let us humbly thank God for our Chaſtiſement and Viſitation. And let us
have but a very little Patience, and we ſhall ſee and underſtand his
righteous Judgments. We ſhall ſee the Difference he makes betwixt Children
and Enemies, and that <hi>we</hi> were not in <hi>Rome</hi>'s Stead, but in our
own neceſſary refining Fire, we ſhall ſee our Adverſaries Mirth be
turned into Mourning; and that the <hi>Jucolae Terrae, &amp; Reges Terrae,</hi>
ſhall weep <pb n="11" facs="tcp:151715:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>and mourn, and ſtand afar off, and
ſay, <hi>Alas, alas, for that great City Babylon, that ſtrong City, in one
Hour thy Judgments are come.</hi> Amen. Be it ſo. And NOW, though the
preceding Diſcourſe under <hi>Seven</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Heads, ſhould be
Sealed up to others like the Seven Thunders, yet to me they have ſpoke very
loudly, and I would ſpeak God's Praiſe in Words as loud, if I could, and
therefore ſhall call a great Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to aſſiſt me, I mean The
Church, and in <hi>Her</hi> Words ſay; <hi>Worthy art thou, O Bleſſed
Jeſus, to take the Book and open the Seals, becauſe thou waſt ſlain,
and haſt redeemed us to God by thy Blood, out of every Tribe and Tongue, and
People and Nation, and made us Kings and Prieſts unto God, and we ſhall
reign on Earth. Worthy is the Lamb to receive, Pover, and Wiſdom, and Riches,
and Strength, and Honour, and Bleſſing, for ever more. Great and Marvellous
are thy Works, Lord God Almighty, Juſt and True are thy Ways. Thou King of
Saints, who ſhall not fear thee, O Lord, and glorifie thy Name? For thou only
art Holy; All Nations ſhall come and worſhip before thee, for thy Judgments
are made manifeſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
